<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://wab.uib.no/cost-a32/skjema/wab_OA.rng" type="xml" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
	xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">



	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="WS" key="Facsimile: CC BY-NC 4.0. Original at the Wren Library, Trinity College, Cambridge, where in 2014-15, on the request of the Wittgenstein Archives at the University of Bergen (WAB) and with the generous financial support of the Stanhill Foundation, London, this scan was produced. The image was post-processed at WAB and is reproduced here by permission of The Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge, and the University of Bergen, Bergen. The sale, further reproduction or use of this image for commercial purposes without prior permission from the copyright holder is prohibited. © 2015 The Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; The University of Bergen, Bergen."> Ts-207 [so-called Lecture on Ethics] (WL)</title>
				<title xml:id="Ts-207" n="Ts-207" type="main" xml:lang="en"/>
				<author>
					<persName xml:id="wittgenstein" key="Wittgenstein, Ludwig">Ludwig Wittgenstein</persName>
				</author>
				<editor>
					<orgName ref="http://wab.uib.no/">WAB</orgName> (directors: Claus Huitfeldt 1990-2000,  Alois Pichler 2001-). Responsible editor for this transcription: <persName>Alois Pichler</persName>
				</editor>
				<funder>Trinity College, Cambridge; Oxford University Press, Oxford;  Uni Research, Bergen; University of Bergen, Bergen; L. Meltzers Høyskolefond, Bergen; COST Action A32, Brussels; eContent+ DISCOVERY, Luxembourg; ICT PSP DM2E,  Brussels</funder>

				<respStmt>
					<name>Odin Thorbjørnsen, Alois Pichler</name>
					<resp>transcription in MECS-WIT markup: 1997</resp>
				</respStmt>

				<respStmt>
					<name>Alois Pichler</name>
					<resp>2001-: coordination and editorial guidelines; amendments; conversion from MECS-WIT to XML-TEI; XML-TEI markup</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<name>Claus Huitfeldt, Kjersti Bjørnestad Berg, Sindre Sørensen, MLCD project</name>
					<resp>2001: parser for conversion from MECS to XML</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<name>Vemund Olstad, Øyvind L. Gjesdal, Tone Merete Bruvik</name>
					<resp>2002-: stylesheets</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<name>Tone Merete Bruvik, Øyvind L. Gjesdal</name>
					<resp>2006-: XML-TEI validation</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<name>Heinz Wilhelm Krüger, Deirdre C. P. Smith</name>
					<resp>2006-09: amendments; XML-TEI markup</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<name>Špela Vidmar</name>
					<resp>2013-14: proofreading of normalized transcription</resp>
				</respStmt>


				<respStmt>
					<name>Nivedita Gangopadhyay </name>
					<resp>2018: proofreading of normalized transcription</resp>
				</respStmt>

				<respStmt>
					<name>Claus Huitfeldt</name>
					<resp>2020: spell-check</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<name>Michael Biggs, Hans Biesenbach</name>
					<resp>1990-: the transcription includes links to graphics provided by Michael Biggs: "Ludwig Wittgenstein: A Visual Concordance to the Published Works", Minerva Vol. 2 (1998) [http://www.minerva.mic.ul.ie/vol2/Ver_33/index.htm] or Hans Biesenbach.</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>

			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="URL">http://wab.uib.no/cost-a32_xml/Ts-207_OA.xml</idno>

				<publisher>Wittgenstein Archives at the University of Bergen (WAB)</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Bergen</pubPlace>
				<idno type="URL">http://www.wittgensteinsource.org/Ts-207_n</idno>
				<idno type="URL">http://www.wittgensteinsource.org/Ts-207_d</idno>
				<idno type="URL">http://www.wittgensteinsource.org/Ts-207_f</idno>


				<idno type="URL">http://wittgensteinonline.no/</idno>
				<availability xml:lang="en">
					<p>Copyright holders: The Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; University of Bergen, Bergen. Released under the Creative Commons General Public License Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
				</availability>

			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc xml:lang="en">
				<p>Tba. </p>
			</sourceDesc>

		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="http://philpapers.org/">
					<term>Philosophy of Language</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>

	</teiHeader>
	
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<ab>
				<seg type="wabmarks-secml_h">​</seg>
				<seg type="publ">
					<s type="es">Ladies and <c type="c">G</c>entlemen,<lb rend="hl"/>
					</s>
					<s type="es" rend="indl_9">Before I begin to
					speak about my subject proper let me make a<lb/>
					few introductory
					remarks.</s>

					<s type="es">
						<c type="k">I</c> feel I shall have great difficulties in<lb/>
					communicating my
					thoughts to you and I think some of them may be<lb/>
					diminished by mentioning
					them to you beforehand.</s>

					<s type="es">The first one, which<lb/>
					almost I need not mention, is, that English is not
					my native tongue and<lb/>
					my expression therefore often lacks that precision
					and subtilty which<lb/>
					would be desirable if one talks
					about a difficult subject.</s>

					<s type="es">All I can do<lb/>
					is to ask you to make my task easier by trying to get at my meaning<lb/>	
					inspite of the faults which I will constantly be committing against the<lb/>
					English grammar.</s>

					<s type="es">The second difficulty I will mention is this, that<lb/>
					probably many of you
					come up to this lecture of mine with slightly wrong<lb/>
					expectations.</s>

					<s type="es">And to set you right in this point I will say a few<lb/>
					words about the
					reason for choosing the subject I have chosen: <c type="c">W</c>hen<lb/>
					your
					former secretary honoured me by asking me to read a paper to your<lb/>
					society, my first thought was that I would certainly do it and my second<lb/>
					thought was that if I was to have the opportunity to speak to you I<lb/>
					should speak about something which I am keen on communicating to you and<lb/>
					that I should not misuse this opportunity to give you a lecture about,<lb/>
					say, logic.</s>

					<s type="es">
						<c type="k">I</c> call this a misuse for to explain a scientific matter to<lb/>
					you it
					would need a course of lectures and not an hour's paper.</s>

					<s type="es">An<lb/>
					other alternative would have been to give you what's called a
					popular<lb rend="divl"/>
					scientific lecture, that is a lecture intended to make you
					believe that<lb/>
					you understand a thing which actually you don't
					understand, and to<lb/>
					gratify what I believe to be one of the lowest desires
					of modern people,<lb/>
					namely the superficial curiosity about the latest
					discoveries of science.<lb/>
					</s>
					
					<s type="es">
					<c type="k">I</c> rejected these alternatives and decided to talk to you about a
					subject<lb/>
					which seems to me to be of general importance, hoping that it may
					help<lb/>
					to clear up your thoughts about this subject (even if you
					should<lb/>
					<fw type="pagen" place="top left">2)</fw> entirely disagree with what I will say
					about it).</s>

					<s type="es">My third and last<lb/>
					difficulty is one which, in fact, adheres to most
					lengthy philosophical<lb/>
					lectures and it is this, that the hearer is
					incapable of seeing both<lb/>
					the road he is led and the goal which it leads
					to.</s>

					<s type="es">That is to say: he<lb/>
					either thinks: <seg type="q">“I understand
					all he says, but what on earth is he driving<lb/>
					at”</seg> or else he
					thinks <seg type="q">“I see what he's driving at, but how on earth is<lb/>
					he going to get there”</seg>.
					</s>

					<s type="es">All I can do is again to ask you to be patient<lb/>
					and to hope that in the
					end you may see both the way and where it leads<lb/>
					to. ‒ ‒ ‒</s>
				</seg>
			</ab>

			<ab>
				<seg type="wabmarks-secml_h">​</seg>
				<seg type="publ">
					<s type="es" rend="indl_8">
						<c type="k">I</c> will now begin.</s>
					
							<rs type="extref" key="Moore, George Edward: Principia Ethica">
					<s type="es">My subject, as you know, is <term xml:id="fld1" ana="onto:Field">
						<c type="c">E</c>thics
					</term>thics and I will<lb/>
					adopt the
					explanation of that term which <persName xml:id="moore" ana="onto:Person" key="Moore, George Edward">Prof. Moore</persName> has given in his<lb/>
					book
					<seg type="q">
						<bibl xml:id="src1" ana="onto:WittgensteinExternalSource" ref="#moore">“Principia Ethica”</bibl>
					</seg>.
					</s>
						
					<s type="es">He says: <seg xml:id="persp1" ana="onto:Perspective" corresp="#fld1" ref="#moore">
					“<c type="c">E</c>thics is the general enquiry into<lb/>what is good.”
					</seg>
					</s>
							</rs>
					
					<s xml:id="persp2" type="es" ana="onto:Perspective" ref="#wittgenstein" corresp="#fld1">
						Now I am going to use the term <c type="c">E</c>thics in a slightly<lb/>
						wider sense,
						in a sense in fact which includes what I believe to be the<lb/>
						most essential
						part of what is generally called 
						<term xml:id="fld2" ana="onto:Field">
							<c type="c">A</c>esthetics
						</term>.
					</s>
							<rs type="extref" key="Galton, Francis: Memories of my Life">
						
					<s type="es">And to make<lb/>
					you see as clearly as possible what I take to be the
					subject matter of<lb/>
						<c type="c">E</c>thics I will put before you a number of more or
					less synonymous expres<lb rend="shyphen"/>
					sions each of which could be substituted for
					the above definition, and<lb/>
					by enumerating them I want to produce the same
					sort of effect which<lb/>
					<persName xml:id="galton" ana="onto:Person" key="Galton, Francis">Galton
					</persName> produced when he took a number of photos of
					different faces<lb/>
					on the same photographic plate in order to get the
					picture of the<lb/>
					typical features they all had in common.
					</s>
							</rs>
					
					<s type="es">And as by showing to you such a<lb/>
					collective photo I could make you see
					what is the typical – say – <lb/>
					Chinese face;
					so if you look through the row of synonyms which I will put<lb/>
					before you,
					you will, I hope, be able to see the characteristic<lb/>
					features they all
					have in common and these are the characteristic<lb/>
					features of
					<c type="c">E</c>thics.
					</s>
					
					<s type="es">
						Now instead of saying 
						<seg type="q">“<c type="c">E</c>thics is the enquiry into<lb/>what is good”</seg> 
						I could have said
						<seg xml:id="ex1" type="example" ana="onto:Exemplification" corresp="#persp1">
							<c type="c">E</c>thics is the enquiry into what is valuable
						</seg>, or,
						<seg xml:id="ex2" type="example" ana="onto:Exemplification" corresp="#persp1">
							into what is really important
						</seg>, or
						<seg xml:id="ex3" type="example" ana="onto:Exemplification" corresp="#persp1">
							the enquiry into the meaning of life
						</seg>, or
						<seg xml:id="ex4" type="example" ana="onto:Exemplification" corresp="#persp1">
							what makes life worth living
						</seg>, or
						<seg xml:id="ex5" type="example" ana="onto:Exemplification" corresp="#persp1">
							the right way of living
						</seg>.
					</s>


					<s type="es">
						<c type="k">I</c> believe if you look at all these phrases<lb/>
					you will get a rough
					idea as to what it is that <c type="c">E</c>thics is concerned with.<lb/>
					</s>
					<s type="es"> Now the first thing that strikes one about all these expressions is
					that<lb/>
					each of them is actually used in two very different senses.
					</s>

					<s type="es">
						<c type="k">I</c> will call<lb/>
					them the trivial or relative sense on the one hand
					and the ethical or<lb/>
					absolute sense on the other.</s>
					<s type="es">If for instance I say that this is a <emph rend="us1">good</emph>
					<lb/>
					chair this means
					that the chair serves a certain predetermined purpose and<lb/>
					the word <corr type="tra">“</corr>good<corr type="tra">”</corr>
					here has only meaning so far as this purpose has been pre<lb rend="shyphen"/>
					viously
					fixed upon.
					</s>

					<s type="es">In fact the word <seg type="q">
					<corr type="tra">“</corr>good<corr type="tra">”</corr>
					</seg> in the
					relative sense simply<lb/>
					means coming up to a certain predetermined
					standard.
					</s>

					<s type="es">Thus when we say that<lb/>
					this man is a good pianist we mean that he can
					play pieces of a certain<lb/>
					degree of difficulty with a certain degree of
					dexterity.
					</s>

					<s type="es">And similarly if<lb/>
					I say that it is <emph rend="us1">important</emph> for me not to
					catch cold I mean that catching<lb/>
					a cold produces certain describable
					disturbances in my life and if I say<lb/>
					that this is the <emph rend="us1">right</emph>
					road <del type="dnpc">that it</del> I mean that it's the right road rela<lb rend="shyphen"/>
					tive
					to a certain goal.
					</s>

					<s type="es">Used in this way these expressions don't present<lb/>
					any difficult or
					deep problems.</s>
					<s type="es">But this is not how <c type="c">E</c>thics uses them.<lb/>
					</s>

					<s type="es">Supposing that I could play tennis and one of you saw me playing and
					said<lb/>
					<seg type="q">“well you play pretty badly”</seg> and suppose I
					answered <seg type="q">“I know, I'm playing<lb/>
					badly but I don't want
					to play any better”</seg>, all the other man could say<lb/>
					would be
					<seg type="q">“<c type="c">A</c>h then that's all right”</seg>.
					</s>

					<s type="es">But suppose I had told one of you a<lb/>
					preposterous lie and he came up to
					me and said <seg type="q">“<c type="c">Y</c>ou're behaving like a<lb/>
					beast”</seg> and then I were to say <seg type="q">“I know I behave
					badly, but then I don't<lb/>
					want to behave any better”</seg>, could
					he then say <seg type="q">“<c type="c">A</c>h, then that's all
					right”</seg>?
					</s>

					<lb/>
					<s type="es">Certainly not; he would say <seg type="q">“<c type="c">W</c>ell, you <emph rend="us1">ought</emph>
					to want to behave better”</seg>.
					</s>
					<lb/>
					<s type="es">Here you have an absolute judgment of value, whereas the first instance<lb/>
					was one of a relative judgment.
					</s>

					<s type="es">The essence of this difference seems to<lb/>
					be obviously this:
					<c type="c">E</c>very judgment of relative value is a mere statement of<lb/>
					facts and can therefore be put in such a
					form that it loses all the<lb/>
					appearance of a judgment of value:
					<c type="c">I</c>nstead of saying <seg type="q">“this is the right way<lb/>
					to
					<name key="Granchester">Granchester</name>
					<corr type="tra">”</corr>
					</seg> I could equally well have
					said <seg type="q">“this is the right way you<lb/>
					have to go if you want to get
					to <name key="Granchester">Granchester</name> in the shortest time”</seg>,
					<seg type="q">
					<corr type="tra">“</corr>this<lb/>
					man is a good runner<corr type="tra">”</corr>
					</seg>
					simply means that he runs a certain number of miles in<lb/>
					a certain number
					of minutes, <abbr corresp="and so forth.">a.s.f.</abbr>
					</s>
					
					<s type="es">
						<seg xml:id="clm1"
							ana="onto:Point"
							ref="#wittgenstein"
							corresp="#fld1">
							although all judgments of relative value can be shown to be mere statements
							of facts, no statement of fact can ever be, or imply, a judgment of
							<emph rend="us1">absolute</emph> value
						</seg>
					</s>
					
					
					<s type="es">
						<seg xml:id="ex6"
							ana="onto:Exemplification"
							corresp="#clm1">
							Let me explain this: <c type="c">S</c>uppose one of you were an omniscient
							person and therefore knew all the movements of all the bodies in the world
							dead or alive and that he also knew all the states of mind of all human
							beings that ever lived, and suppose this man wrote all he knew in a big
							book, then this book would contain the whole description of the world; and
							what I want to say is, that this book would contain nothing that we would
							call an <emph rend="us1">ethical</emph> judgment or anything that would logically imply such a
							judgment.
						</seg>
					</s>

					<s type="es">It would of course contain all relative judgments of value and<lb/>
					all true
					scientific propositions and in fact all true propositions that can<lb/>
					be
					made.
					</s>

					<s type="es">But all the facts described would, as it were, stand on the same<lb/>
					level
					and in the same way all propositions stand on the same level.
					</s>

					<s type="es">There<lb/>
					are no propositions which, in any absolute sense, are sublime,
					important,<lb/>
					or trivial.</s>
					<persName xml:id="shakespeare" ana="onto:Person" key="Shakespeare, William"/>
					
					<s type="es">
						Now perhaps some of you will agree to that and be reminded of<lb/>
						<bibl xml:id="src2" ana="onto:WittgensteinExternalSource" ref="#shakespeare">Hamlet</bibl>'s words:
						<seg xml:id="persp3" ana="onto:Perspective" ref="#shakespeare" corresp="#fld1" source="#src2" type="q">
							“Nothing is either good or bad, but thinking makes it so.”
						</seg>
					</s>


						
					<lb/>
					<s type="es">But this again could lead to a misunderstanding.</s>
					<s type="es">What Hamlet
					says seems to<lb/>
					imply that good and bad, though not qualities of the world
					outside us, are<lb/>
					attributes of our states of mind.</s>
					<s type="es">But what I mean is that a state of mind,<lb/>
					so far as we mean by that a
					fact which we can describe, is in no ethical<lb/>
					sense good or bad.
					</s>
					

					<s type="es">If for instance in our world-book we read the descrip<lb rend="shyphen"/>
					tion of a
					murder with all its details physical and psychological the mere<lb/>
					description of these facts will contain nothing which we could call an<lb/>
					<emph rend="us1">ethical</emph> proposition.
					</s>

					<s type="es">The murder will be on exactly the same level as any<lb/>
					other event, for
					instance the falling of a stone.
					</s>

					<s type="es">Certainly the reading of<lb/>
					this description might cause us pain or rage
					or any other emotion, or we<lb/>
					might read about the pain or rage caused by
					this murder in other people<lb/>
					when they heard of it, but there will simply
					be facts, facts and facts but<lb/>
					no <c type="c">E</c>thics. –
					</s>
					
					<seg xml:id="clm2" ana="onto:Point" corresp="#fld1" ref="#wittgenstein">
						<s type="es">And now I must say that if I contemplate what <c type="c">E</c>thics really<lb/>
							would have to be if there were such a science, this result seems to me<lb/>
							quite obvious.</s>
						
						<s type="es">It seems to me obvious that nothing we could ever think or<lb/>
							say should be <emph rend="us1_ch">the</emph> thing.</s>
						
						<s type="es">That we cannot write a scientific book, the subject matter of which<lb/>
							could be intrinsically sublime and above all other subject matters.</s>
					</seg>

					<s type="es">
						<c type="k">I</c> can only describe my feeling by the metaphor, <seg xml:id="met1" ana="onto:Metaphor" corresp="#clm2">
						that, if<lb/>
						a man could write a book on <c type="c">E</c>thics which really was a book on <c type="c">E</c>thics,
						this<lb/>
						book would, with an explosion, destroy all the other books in the world.
					</seg> – <lb/>
					</s>
					
					<seg xml:id="clm3" type="es" ana="onto:Point" ref="#wittgenstein" corresp="#fld3">
						Our words used as we use them in 
						<term xml:id="fld3" ana="onto:Field">science</term>,
						are vessels capable only of con<lb rend="shyphen"/> 
						taining and conveying meaning and sense, 
						<emph rend="us1">natural</emph> meaning 
						an<add rend="our_h">d</add> sense.
					</seg>

				</seg>
			</ab>

			<ab>
				<seg type="wabmarks-secml_h">​</seg>
				<seg type="publ"><lb/>
					<s type="es">
						<seg xml:id="clm4" ana="onto:Point" ref="#wittgenstein" corresp="#fld1">
							Ethics, if it is anything, is supernatural and our words will only
							express<lb/>facts;
						</seg>
						<seg xml:id="met2" ana="onto:Metaphor" corresp="#clm4">
							as a teacup will only hold a teacup full of water and if I
							were to<lb/>
							pour a gallon over it.
						</seg>
					</s>
					
					<s type="es">
						<seg xml:id="clm5" ana="onto:Point" ref="#wittgenstein" corresp="#fld3">
							<c type="k">I</c> said that so far<del type="dnpc_h"/>
							as facts and prop<add rend="el_h">o</add>sitions<lb/>
							are concerned there is only relative value and relative good, right <abbr type="abb">etc.</abbr>
						</seg>
					</s>

					<lb/>
					<s type="es">
						
							And let me, before I go <add rend="our_h">o</add>n, illustrate this by a rather obvious example.<lb/>
						<seg xml:id="ex7" ana="onto:Exemplification" corresp="#clm5">The right road is the road which leads to an arbitrarily predetermined end<lb/>
							and it is quite clear to us all that there is no sense in talking about the<lb/>
							right road apart from such a predetermined goal.
						</seg>
					</s>

					<s type="es">Now let us see what we<lb/>
					could possibly mean by the expression 
					</s>
					
					<s type="es">
						<seg xml:id="ex8" ana="onto:Exemplification" corresp="#clm5">
							“<emph rend="us1">the</emph> absolutely right road”. I think<lb/>
							it would be the road which <emph rend="us1">everybody</emph> on seeing
							it would, <emph rend="us1">with logical<lb/>
								necessity</emph> have to go, or be ashamed for
							not going.
						</seg>
					</s>
					
					<s type="es">
						<seg xml:id="ex9" ana="onto:Exemplification" corresp="#clm5">
							And similarly the<lb/>
							<emph rend="us1">absolute</emph>
							<emph rend="us1">good</emph>, if it is a
							describable state of affairs would be one which<lb/>
							everybody, independent of
							his tastes and inclinations, would <emph rend="us1">necessarily</emph><lb/>
							bring about or
							feel guilty for not bringing about. And I want to say that<lb/>
							such a state of affairs is a chimera.
						</seg>
					</s>


					<s type="es">
					</s>

					<s type="es">No state of affairs has in itself,<lb/>
					what I would like to call, the coercive
					power of an absolute judge. –
					</s>
					<lb/>

					<s type="es">Then what have all of us who, like myself, are still tempted to use
					such<lb/>
					expressions as <seg type="q">“absolute good”</seg>,
					<seg type="q">“absolute value”</seg>
					<abbr type="abb">etc<corr type="tra">.</corr>
					</abbr>,
					what have we in mind<lb/>
					and what do we try to express?
					</s>

					<s type="es">Now whenever I try to make this clear to<lb/>
					myself it is natural that I
					should recall cases in which I would certainly<lb/>
					use these expressions and
					I am then in the situation and in which you would<lb/>
					be if, for instance, I
					were to give you a lecture on the psychology of<lb/>
					pleasure.
					</s>

					<s type="es">What you would do then would be to try and recall some typical<lb/>
					situation in which you always felt pleasure.
					</s>

					<s type="es">For, bearing this situation in<lb/>
					mind, all I should say to you would
					become concrete and, as it were,<lb/>
					control<corr type="tran">l</corr>able.
					</s>

					<s type="es">One man would perhaps choose as his stock example the sensa<lb rend="shyphen"/>
					tion
					when taking a walk on a fine summer's day.
					</s>

					<s type="es">Now in this situation I am<lb/>
					if I want to fix my mind on what I mean by
					absolute or ethical value.<lb/>
					</s>

					<s type="es">And there, in my case, it always happens that the idea of one
					particular<lb/>
					experience presents itself to me which therefore is, in a
					sense, my ex<lb rend="shyphen"/>
					perience <seg type="ct">
					<corr type="trs">
					<orig type="trs1">for</orig>
					<reg type="trs2"> par</reg>
					</corr> excellence</seg> and
					this is the reason why, in talking to you now,<lb/>
					I will use this experience
					as my first and foremost example.
					</s>

					<s type="es">(As I have<lb/>
					said before, this is an entirely personal matter and
					others would find<lb/>
					other examples more striking<corr type="tra">.</corr>)
					</s>

					<s type="es">
						<c type="k">I</c> will describe this experience in order, if<lb/>
					possible, to make
					you recall the same or similar experiences, so that we<lb/>
					may have a common
					ground for our investigation.
					</s>

					<s type="es">
					<c type="k">I</c> believe the best way of<lb/>
					describing it is to say that when I
					have it <emph rend="us1">I wonder at the existence of<lb/>
					the world.</emph>
					</s>

					<s type="es">And I am then inclined to use such phrases as <seg type="q">“how
					extraordi<lb rend="shyphen"/>
					nary that anything should exist”</seg> or
					<seg type="q">“how extraordinary that the world<lb/>
					should
					exist”</seg>.
					</s>

					<rs type="extref" key="Anzengruber, Ludwig: Die Kreuzelschreiber">
					<s type="es">
					<c type="k">I</c> will mention another experience straight away which I also<lb/>
					know
					and which others of you might be acquainted with: it is, what one<lb/>
					might call, the experience of feeling <emph rend="us1">absolutely</emph> safe.
					</s>
						
					<s type="es">
					<c type="k">I</c> mean the state of<lb/>
					mind in which one is inclined to say
					<seg type="q">“I am safe, nothing can injure me<lb/>
					whatever
					happens”</seg>.
					</s>
					</rs>

					<s type="es">Now let me consider these experiences, for, I believe,<lb/>
					they exhibit the
					very characteristics we try to get clear about.
					</s>

					<s type="es">And there<lb/>
					the first thing I have to say is, that
					the verbal expression which we give<lb/>
					to these experiences is
					nonsense!
					</s>

					<s type="es">If I say <seg type="q">“I wonder at the existence of<lb/>
					the
					world<add rend="el">”</add>
					</seg> I am misusing language.
					</s>

					<s type="es">Let me explain this: <c type="c">I</c>t has a perfectly<lb/>
					good and clear
					sense to say that I wonder at something being the case, we<lb/>
					all understand
					what it means to say that I wonder at the size of a dog which<lb/>
					is bigger
					than anyone I have ever seen before or at any thing which, in the<lb/>
					common
					sense of the word, is extraordinary.
					</s>

					<s type="es">In every such case I wonder at<lb/>
					something being the case which I
					<emph rend="us1">could</emph> conceive <emph rend="us1">not</emph> to be the case.
					</s>

					<s type="es">
					<c type="k">I</c> wonder<lb/>
					at the size of this dog because I could conceive of a
					dog of another, namely<lb/>
					the ordinary size, at which I should not
					wonder.
					</s>

					<s type="es">To say <seg type="q">“I wonder at such and<lb/>
					such being the
					case<add rend="el_h">”</add>
					</seg> has only sense if I can imagine it not to be
					the case.<lb/>
					</s>

					<s type="es">In this sense one can wonder at the existence of, say, a house when one
					sees<lb/>
					it and has not visited it for a long time and has imagined that it
					had been<lb/>
					pulled down in the meantime.
					</s>

					<s type="es">But it is nonsense to say that I wonder at the<lb/>
					existence of the world,
					because I cannot imagine it not existing.
					</s>

					<s type="es">
					<c type="k">I</c> could of<lb/>
					course wonder at the world round me being as it
					is.
					</s>

					<s type="es">If for instance I had this<lb/>
					experience while looking into the blue sky,
					I could wonder at the sky being<lb/>
					blue as opposed to the case when it's
					clouded.</s>
					<s type="es">But that's not what I mean.<lb/>
					</s>

					<s type="es">
					<c type="k">I</c> am wondering at the sky being <emph rend="us1">whatever it is.</emph>
					</s>

					<s type="es">One might be tempted to say<lb/>
					that what I am wondering at is a
					t<del type="dnpc_h">
					<corr type="npcn">
					<gap extent="words_1"/>
					</corr>
					</del>
					<add rend="i_h">au</add>tology, namely at the sky being
					blue or<lb/>
					not blue.
					</s>

					<s type="es">But then it's just nonsense to say that one is wondering at a<lb/>
					t<del type="dn_h">on</del>
					<corr type="tran">au</corr>tology.
					</s>

					<s type="es">Now the same applies to the other experience which I have
					men<lb rend="shyphen"/>
					tioned, the experience of absolute safety.
					</s>

					<s type="es">We all know what it means in ordi<lb rend="shyphen"/>
					nary life to be safe.
					</s>

					<s type="es">
					<c type="k">I</c> am safe in my room, when I cannot be run over by an<lb/>
					omnibus.
					</s>

					<s type="es">
					<c type="k">I</c> am safe <del type="dnpc">when I</del> if I have had whooping cough and cannot
					therefore<lb/>
					get it again.
					</s>

					<s type="es">To be <add rend="im">safe</add> essentially means that it is physically impossible
					that<lb/>
					certain things should happen to me and therefore it's nonsense
					to say that<lb/>
					I am safe <emph rend="us1">whatever</emph> happens.
					</s>

					<s type="es">Again this is a misuse of the word <seg type="q">“safe”</seg> as
					the<lb/>
					other example was a misuse of the word
					<seg type="q">“existence”</seg> or
					<seg type="q">“wondering”</seg>.
					</s>
					
					<seg xml:id="clm6" type="es" ana="onto:Point" ref="#wittgenstein" corresp="#fld1 #fld4">
						Now I want<lb/>
						to impress on you that a certain characteristic misuse of
						our language runs<lb/>
						through <emph rend="us1">all</emph> ethical and
						religious expressions.
					</seg>

					<s type="es">All these expressions <emph rend="us1">seem</emph>,<lb/>
					<seg type="ct">prima facie</seg>, to be just
					<emph rend="us1">similes</emph>.
					</s>

					<s type="es">Thus it seems that when we are using the<lb/>
					word <emph rend="us1">right</emph> in an
					ethical sense, although, what we mean, is not right in its<lb/>
					trivial sense,
					it's something similar, and when we say <seg type="q">“this is a good<lb/>
					fellow”</seg>, although the word
				<seg type="q">
					<corr type="tra">“</corr>good<corr type="tra">”</corr>
					</seg> here doesn't mean
					what it means in the sen<lb rend="shyphen"/>
					tence <seg type="q">“this is a good football
		player”</seg> there seems to be some similarity.<lb/>
					</s>

					<s type="es">And when we say <seg type="q">“this man's life was valuable”</seg>
					we don't mean it in the same<lb/>
					sense in which we would speak of some
					valuable jewelry but there seems to<lb/>
					be some sort of analogy.
					</s>
					
					<seg xml:id="clm7" type="es" ana="onto:Point" ref="#wittgenstein" corresp="#fld4">
						Now all religious terms seem in this sense to be<lb/>
						used as similes or allegorically.
					</seg>
					
					<s xml:id="ex7" ana="onto:Exemplification" corresp="#clm7">
						For when we speak of God and that he
						sees<lb/>
						everything and when we kneel and pray to him all our terms and
						actions<lb/>
						seem to be parts of a great and elaborate allegory which
						represents him as<lb/>
						a human being of great power whose grace we try to win
						<abbr type="abb">etc.</abbr>
						<abbr type="abb">etc.</abbr>
					</s>

					<s type="es">But this<lb/>
					allegory also describes the experience which I have just
					referred to.
					</s>

					<s type="es">For,<lb/>
					the first of them is, I believe, exactly what people were
					referring to when<lb/>
					they said that God had
					created the world; and the experience of absolute<lb/>
					safety has been
					described by saying that we feel safe in the hands of God.<lb/>
					</s>
					
					<s type="es">A third experience of the same kind is that of feeling guilty and again<lb/>
					this was described by the phrase that God
					disapproves of our conduct.
					</s>

					<s type="es">Thus<lb/>
					in ethical and religious language we seem constantly to be using
					similes.<lb/>
					</s>

					<s type="es">But a simile must be the simile for <emph rend="us1">something.</emph>
					</s>

					<s type="es">And if I can describe a fact<lb/>
					by means of a simile I must also be able
					to drop the simile and to<lb/>
					describe the facts without it.
					</s>

					<s type="es">Now in our case as soon as we try to drop<lb/>
					the simile and simply to
					state the facts which stand behind it, we find,<lb/>
					that there are no such
					facts.
					</s>

					<s type="es">And so, what at first appeared to be a <del type="dnpc_h"/>
					<lb/>
					simile, now
					seems to be mere nonsense. –
					</s>

				</seg>
				<seg type="publ">
					<s type="es">Now the three experiences which<lb/>
					I have mentioned to you (and I could
					have added others) seem to those who<lb/>
					have experienced them, for
					instance to me, to have in some sense an<lb/>
					intrinsic, absolute
					value.
					</s>

					<s type="es">But when I say they are experiences, surely,<lb/>
					they are facts; they have
					taken place then and there, lasted a certain<lb/>
					 definite time and consequently are
					describable.
					</s>

					<s type="es">And so from what I have<lb/>
					said some minutes ago I must admit it is
					nonsense to say that they have<lb/>
					absolute value.
					</s>
					
					<seg xml:id="clm8" type="es" ana="onto:Point" ref="#wittgenstein" corresp="#fld1">
						And here I have arrived at the main point of this paper:<lb/>
						it is the paradox that an experience, a fact should seem to have absolute value.
					</seg>

					
					<s type="es">And I will make my point still more acute by saying <seg type="q">“it is<lb/>
					the paradox that an experience, a fact, should seem to have supernatural<lb/>
					value<corr type="tra">”</corr>
					</seg>.
					</s>

					<s type="es">Now there is a way in which I would be tempted to meet this
					paradox.<lb/>
					</s>

					<s type="es">Let me first consider, again, our first experience of wondering at the<lb/>
					existence of the world and let me describe it in a slightly different
					way
					<lb/>
					<c type="c">W</c>e all know what in ordinary life would be
					called a miracle.</s>
					
					<s type="es">It obviously<lb/>
					is simply an event the like of which we never have
					seen.
					</s>
					<lb/>

					<s type="es">Now suppose such an event happened.</s>
					<s type="es"><lb/>Take the case that one of you suddenly
					grew a lion<corr type="tra">'</corr>s head
					and began to roar.
					</s>
					<lb/>
					<s type="es">Certainly that would be as extraordinary a thing as I can
					imagine.
					</s>
					<lb/>
					
					<s type="es">Now whenever we should have recovered from<lb/>
					our surprise, what I would
					suggest would be to fetch a doctor and have the<lb/>
					case scientifically
					investigated and if it were not for hurting him I would<lb/>
					have him
					vivisected.
					</s>

					<s type="es">And where would the miracle have got to?</s>
					<s type="es">For it is<lb/>
					clear that when we look at it in this way everything
					miraculous has dis<lb rend="shyphen"/>
					appeared; unless what we mean by this term is
					merely that a fact has not<lb/>
					yet been explained by science which again
					means that we have hitherto<lb/>
					failed to group this fact with others in a
					scientific system.
					</s>

					<s type="es">This shows<lb/>
					that it is absurd to say <seg type="q">“science has proved
					that there are no miracles”</seg>.
					</s>
					<lb/>

					<s type="es">The truth is that the scientific way of looking at a fact is not the
					way<lb/>
					to look at it as a miracle.
					</s>

					<s type="es">For imagine whatever fact you may, it is not in<lb/>
					itself miraculous in
					the absolute sense of that term.
					</s>

					<s type="es">For we see now that<lb/>
					we have been using the word
					<seg type="q">“miracle”</seg> in a relative and an absolute
					sense.<lb/>
					</s>

					<s type="es">And I will now describe the experience of wondering at the existence of
					the<lb/>
					world by saying: it is the experience of seeing the world as a
					miracle.<lb/>
					</s>

					<s type="es">Now I am tempted to say that the right expression in language for the<lb/>
					miracle of the existence of the world, though it is not any proposition
					<emph rend="us1">in</emph>
					<lb/>
					language, is the existence of language itself.
					</s>

					<s type="es">But what then does it mean<lb/>
					to be aware of this miracle at some
					times and not at other times<choice type="o_h">
					<orig type="o1">.</orig>
					<orig type="o2">?</orig>
					</choice>
					</s>

					<s type="es">For all<lb/>
					I have said by shifting the expression of the miraculous from
					an expression<lb/>
					<emph rend="us1">by means of</emph> language to the expression <emph rend="us1">by
					the existence</emph> of language, all I<lb/>
					have said is again that we cannot
					express what we want to express and that<lb/>
					all we <emph rend="us1">say</emph> about the
					absolute miraculous remains nonsense. –
					</s>

					<s type="es">Now the answer<lb/>
					to all this will seem perfectly clear to many of
					you.
					</s>

					<s type="es">You will say: <c type="c">W</c>ell,<lb/>
					if certain experiences constantly tempt
					us to attribute a quality to them<lb/>
					which we call absolute or ethical value
					and importance, this simply shows<lb/>
					that by these words we
					<emph rend="us1">don't</emph> mean nonsense, that after all what we mean by<lb/>
					saying
					that an experience has absolute value <emph rend="us1">is just a fact like other<lb/>
					facts</emph> and that all it comes to is that we have not yet succeeded in
					finding<lb/>
					the correct logical analysis of what we mean by our ethical and
					religious<lb/>
					expressions. –
					</s>

					<s type="es">Now when this is urged against me I at once see clearly,<lb/>
					as it were in
					a flash of light, not only that no description that I can<lb/>
					think of would
					do to describe what I mean by absolute value, but that I<lb/>
					would reject
					every significant description that anybody could possibly<lb/>
					suggest,
					<seg type="ct">
					<emph rend="us1">ab initio</emph>
					</seg>, on the ground of its significance.
					</s>

					<s type="es">That is to say: I see<lb/>
					now that these nonsensical expressions were
					not nonsensical because I had<lb/>
					not yet found the correct expressions, but
					that their nonsensicality was<lb/>
					their very essence.
					</s>

					<s type="es">For all I wanted to do with them was just <emph rend="us1">to go beyond</emph>
					<lb/>
					the
					world and that is to say beyond significant language.
					</s>
					
					<seg xml:id="clm9" type="es" ana="onto:Point" ref="#wittgenstein" corresp="#fld1 #fld4">
						My whole tendency<lb/>
						and I believe the tendency of all men who ever tried
						to write or talk<lb/>
						<c type="c">E</c>thics or <term xml:id="fld4" ana="onto:Field">Religion</term> was to run against the
						boundaries of language.
					</seg>


					<s type="es">This<lb/>
					running against the walls of our cage is perfectly, absolutely
					hopeless. – <lb/>
					</s>
					
					<seg xml:id="clm10" type="es" ana="onto:Point" ref="#wittgenstein" corresp="#fld1 #fld3">
						Ethics so far as it springs from the desire to say something about the<lb/>
						ultimate meaning of life, the absolute good, the absolute valuable, can be<lb/>
						no science.
						
						<lb/>What it says does not add to our knowledge in any sense.
						
						<lb/>But it<lb/>
						is a document of a tendency in the human mind which I personally
						cannot help<lb/>
						respecting deeply and I would not for my life ridicule it.
					</seg>

				</seg>
			</ab>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>